世[よ]:world/society/age, 世[せい]:counter for generations|epoch
（ヤサコ）人の世のウワサでは―
According to rumors circulating among some people,
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
会いたい人のことを
ずっと考えていると
if you think constantly about a person you want to meet,
不意[ふい]:sudden/abrupt/unexpected, ばったり:with a clash/with a thud|unexpectedly (meeting someone), 出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
不意にばったり出会うことが
あるそうです
you'll suddenly end up seeing them.
研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
（フミエ）研究 私も手伝うわ
I'll help you with the research.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority
（ヤサコ）
私も　同じクラブじゃない
Me too!
We're in the same club after all!
…とは言ってみたものの
But even though we said that,
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
何をどうすりゃあ
手伝ったことになるのか
we really have no idea how to help him out.
さっぱり:feeling refreshed/feeling relieved|neat
さっぱりだわ…
イリーガル:illegal, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
まずは イリーガルを探すことね
For starters, we need to find an Illegal.
イリーガル:illegal
そして そのイリーガルが
Then we have to verify whether or not the Illegals
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 異常[いじょう]:strangeness/abnormality/disorder, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up
電脳ナビの異常に
関係あるかどうか調べるのよ
have anything to do with the cybernavis malfunctioning.
そっか
Yeah...
イリーガル:illegal, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
でもイリーガルって
どうやって探すの？
But how do we search for an Illegal?
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
まずは 古い空間を探すのよ
First of all, we have to search the obsolete Space.
交通費[こうつうひ]:traveling expenses/travelling expenses/carfare, 弁当代[べんとうだい]:lunch money
それには交通費 弁当代
But we need to consider the expenses for transport,
food,
お菓子[おかし]:confections/sweets/candy, 代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
それに お菓子代も入れないと
sweets—
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, おしゃべり:chattering/talk|chatty
（ダイチ）先生！
女子がおしゃべりしてます
Teacher!
The girls are talking in class.
授業[じゅぎょう]:lesson/class work/teaching, おしゃべり:chattering/talk|chatty
（マイコ）
授業中におしゃべりしないように
Don't talk during class.
（ダイチ･ナメッチ）ニヒヒ～
すっかり:all/completely/totally, 仕切り[しきり]:partition|settlement of accounts|preliminary warm-up ritual|
フン！　すっかりイサコの仕切りね
That group is totally Isako's.
感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
ヤな感じだわ
How disgusting.
Move Out! Coil Investigation
Agency
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
（ヤサコ）
ねえ さっきの計算
一体なんなの？
Hey, what were those figures you were doing earlier?
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 経費[けいひ]:expenses/cost/outlay
（フミエ）
今回の自由研究の経費よ
I was calculating the budget for our research.
もろもろ:all kinds of things/various things/large number of people, 込み[こみ, コミ]:including/inclusive of|komi, お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors), 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
もろもろ込みで
お年玉１年分は必要だわ
Including all the various expenses, we'll need one year's otoshidama.
（ヤサコ）
えっ そんなに？
Really? That much?
バナナ:banana, お菓子[おかし]:confections/sweets/candy, 含める[ふくめる]:to include (in a group or scope)|to instruct|to include (a nuance)||, 計算[けいさん]:calculation/reckoning|forecast
バナナを
お菓子に含めない計算でね
And I didn't include banana sweets...
招集[しょうしゅう]:call/summons/convening
メガばあの招集だわ
It's a summons from Mega-baa!
招集[しょうしゅう]:call/summons/convening
招集？
A summons?
招集[しょうしゅう]:call/summons/convening
（フミエ）
で なんなのよ？　招集って
So what's this about?
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 捜索[そうさく]:search (esp. for someone or something missing)/manhunt|legally authorized search of a person, building, etc.
（メガばあ）
うむ 電脳ペットの捜索じゃ
It's a missing pet case.
丁目[ちょうめ]:district of a town/city block (of irregular size), ハムスター:hamster
３丁目のトメさんの
ハムスター マンタが―
Our neighbor, Tome, lost her cyberhamster, Manta.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 行方不明[ゆくえふめい]:missing/unaccounted for
昨日から行方不明になっとる
She lost track of it yesterday.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless
私たち いろいろあって
今 忙しいのよ
We already have our hands full with everything that's happened the past few days!
断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave, メタタグ:META tag, 今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 倍[ばい]:twice/double|times, 値上げ[ねあげ]:price hike/mark-up
（メガばあ）断ったら
メタタグは今までの倍に値上げじゃ
If you don't help me out, I'll charge 'ya double for metatags.
じゃが:potato (Solanum tuberosum), 引き受ける[ひきうける]:to take on|to take over|to guarantee|, ボーナス:bonus, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
じゃが 引き受けたら
ボーナスが出るかもしれん
But if you accept this case,
you might even get a bonus.
ボーナス:bonus
（ヤサコ）ボーナス？
A bonus?
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 絡む[からむ]:to entangle|to pick a quarrel|to be involved with
うむ 実は絡んでおるのじゃ
Yeah. You should know what this case is about:
宝[たから]:treasure
お宝がな！
A treasure!
宝[たから]:treasure
（メガばあ）お宝じゃと？
What?! A treasure?
光る[ひかる]:to shine/to glitter/to be bright
（トメ）うん 光る何かじゃ
Yeah.
It was something shiny.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
確かに そんなものを
わしは持っておった
I'm sure I had something like that.
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
ハッ！　そ… それは
もしかしてキラバグかえ？
Don't... Don't tell me you mean...
a kirabug?
I'm not really sure;
定か[さだか]:definite/sure
（トメ）
はて？　それは定かではないが
光り輝く[ひかりかがやく]:to shine/to glitter
キンキラキンに光り輝く何かじゃ
it was something that was shining.
じゃが:potato (Solanum tuberosum), 秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|, 自信[じしん]:self-confidence/confidence (in oneself)
じゃが わしは
その秘密を覚えておく自信がない
But I felt I wouldn't remember such a secret,
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage
そこでペットのマンタに
記憶させてあるのじゃ
so I recorded it into my pet, Manta.
うーん:hmm/well, 相違[そうい]:difference/discrepancy/variation
うーん…
それはキラバグに相違あるまい
There's no doubt it's a kirabug.
じゃう:to do something completely
ところで
あんた 誰じゃったかのう？
By the way, what's your name again?
キ… キ… キラバグですって！
Wh-What?! A kirabug?!
キラバグって何？
What's a kirabug?
とんでも:unthinkable/unexpected/outrageous, 値[あたい, ね]:price|value|value|, 値[ち]:level/value, 張る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||, 張る[ばる]:to be prominently .../to be persistently ...
とんでもなく値の張るメタバグよ
It's an amazing and highly-valued metabug!
宝[たから]:treasure, 割[わり]:rate|profit|assignment||, お礼[おれい, おんれい]:thanks|manners|bow||, 支払う[しはらう]:to pay
トメさんは そのお宝の３割を
お礼に支払うそうじゃ
Tome has agreed to pay us a third of the treasure's worth.
割[わり]:rate|profit|assignment||
３割も！
A third?!
物入り[ものいり]:expenses
何かと物入りじゃないのかえ？
Don't you have some expenses yourselves?
引き受ける[ひきうける]:to take on|to take over|to guarantee|
もっちろん引き受けるわ！
Say no more! I'll take the case!
見張る[みはる]:to stand watch/to stand guard|to open one's eyes wide
（ダイチ）見張り？
Patrol?
That's right.
現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
（イサコ）
そうよ もし誰か現れたら―
Should anyone come here,
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, 荒らす[あらす]:to lay waste|to invade|to troll (e.g. web forums), 追い払う[おいはらう, おいぱらう]:to drive away/to clear/to scatter
暗号式を荒らさないように
追い払うのよ
you have to prevent them from deciphering the encryption key.
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|
（ガチャギリ）暗号式？
The... encryption key?
踏む[ふむ]:to step on|to experience|to estimate||
（イサコ）踏むな！
（一同）えっ？
Don't step on it!
そいつ:he/she|that, デリケート:delicate/sensitive/subtle
そいつはデリケートなんだ
It's delicate stuff.
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 組む[くむ]:to cross (legs or arms)|to put together|to braid||, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
今回 初めて組んだ暗号だから
It's an encode I just made,
きっかけ:chance/start/cue, 誤[ご]:mistake/error, 作動[さどう]:operation/functioning/running
何がきっかけで
誤作動するか分からん
so I don't know whether it'll malfunction or not.
近づける[ちかづける]:to bring near/to put close/to let come near, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
だから 誰も近づけさせるな
That's why you have to make sure no one approaches.
任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office
それがお前たちの今日の任務だ
That's your mission for today.
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
（ダイチ）暗号か
（ガチャギリ）どう使うんだ？
An encryption...
How do you make one?
マニュアル:manual
（イサコ）マニュアルをやる
I'll give you a manual.
壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
壊さなければ
ちょっとは使ってもいい
You can use it for a while,
just don't damage it.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
このクソ暑いのに
ずっと ここにいろって言うのかよ
What the hell?!
You want us to stay here in this heat?!
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
冗談じゃねえ！
You gotta be kidding me!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, アイス:ice, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
お前ら 帰って
アイスでも食おうぜ
Guys, let's go home and buy some ice cream on the way.
You dare disobey me?
逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（イサコ）逆らう気か？
（ダイチ）うっ…
そ… そんなにやりたいなら
お前 自分でやれよ！
If...
If you really want that done,
then do it yourself!
なんだと？
What did you say?
（ダイチ）知ってんだぞ
I know your game!
イマーゴ:imago, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
お前 イマーゴってやつが
使えるんだろ？
You can use that "Imago" thing, can't you?
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 発[はつ]:departure|sending|engine||
それでササッとやっちまえば
一発だろ？
One shot of that stuff, and you can make a mess!
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
頭の悪いヤツは嫌いだわ
I hate stupid people.
（ダイチ）何？
What?
腕[うで]:arm|skill/efforts, 腕[かいな]:arm (esp. upper arm)|counter used to measure the thickness of round objects
（イサコ）自分たちの腕を見てみろ
Look at your arms.
Do you want to challenge me again?
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 勝負[しょうぶ]:victory or defeat/match/contest, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
（イサコ）
もう一度 勝負してあげようか？
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
今度は何年分がいい？
How many years' otoshidama will it be this time?
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
（ダイチ）ま… 待て！　分かった
言うとおりにする
W-Wait!
I got it!
I'll do whatever you want!
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey, 文句を言う[もんくをいう]:to complain/to make a complaint
（イサコ）二度と私に逆らうな
文句を言わずにやれ！
Never disobey me again.
Now shut up and do as I say!
（一同）へ～い
Yes, boss.
辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, 目撃[もくげき]:witnessing/observing/sighting
（ヤサコ）この辺りね
マンタが目撃されたのって
I heard that Manta was spotted in this area.
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 潰れる[つぶれる]:to be crushed|to become useless|to go bankrupt, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 土地[とち, どおじ]:plot of land/lot|locality
（フミエ）みたいね
ここは潰れた会社の土地だから
Yeah, I heard the same thing.
This place is the abandoned site of a company that went bust,
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 墓場[はかば]:graveyard/cemetery, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
こないだのバスの墓場みたいに
so, like the bus graveyard from the other day,
入り込む[はいりこむ, いりこむ]:to go into/to come into|to become complicated, にくい:hateful/abominable|amazing, にくい:difficult to .../hard to ..., 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
サッチーが
入り込みにくい場所なのよ
it's not easily accessible to Satchii.
手分け[てわけ]:division of labour/division of labor/splitting into groups (e.g. to search), 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（フミエ）さあ 手分けして捜そう
Okay, let's split up and search.
O-Okay...
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（フミエ）
私は こっちを捜してみるわ
I'll look over there.
いる
It's here.
イリーガル:illegal, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
イリーガルだ 間違いない
An Illegal.
There's no doubt about it.
I hope this new combination will work all right.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 組み合わせ[くみあわせ]:combination, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
新しい組み合わせが
うまくいけばいいが…
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, ゆがみ:strain/distortion/deformation, ゆがみ:hairdo
んっ… おかしいな
空間にゆがみがある
How strange...
There's a distortion in the Space.
式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
式のどこかが壊れたのか？
Did a function break down somewhere?
ひそひそ:whisperingly, 声[こえ]:voice, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ヤサコ）なんだろう？
このひそひそ声みたいなの
What's that raspy noise?
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
気のせいよね
Nobody's coming, right?
うわー:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（京子(きょうこ)･ヤサコ）うわー！
京子 あんた
なんで ここにいるの？
Kyoko!
What are you doing here?!
遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
京子も遊ぶ
I wanna play, too!
遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
遊んでるわけじゃないの
I'm not playing at all!
しょう:workman/artisan|craft, しょう:quotient|dealing/dealer
もう… しょうがない子ね
Oh geez, you're a real pest...
ハムスター:hamster, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
ほら このハムスターを捜してるの
Look, I'm searching for this hamster.
それなら そこにいるよ
Oh, you mean that one?
なさる:to do
きょ… 京子 待ちなさい！
K-Kyoko!
Wait up!
来た！
Here it is!
おとり:decoy (for hunting)/stool|lure, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
よし！　これなら もう
おとりのペットも使わずに―
Good!
This way, I don't have to use a pet as bait,
呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine)
いつでも呼び出せる
and I can summon it whenever I want!
マンタちゃ～ん どこ？
Manta!
Where are you?
異常[いじょう]:strangeness/abnormality/disorder
異常なしっす
All clear.
りょう:finish/completion/understanding, りょう:hostel/dormitory|bureau (government department beneath a ministry under the ritsuryo system)
（ダイチ）りょうか～い
Roger.
くだる:to descend/to go down|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.), 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
あ～ くだらねえ仕事
What a boring job.
ぶら下がる[ぶらさがる]:to hang from/to dangle/to swing
（ガチャギリ）
でもよ ヤツにぶら下がってれば
But hey,
if we stick with her, we might end up finding a treasure.
宝[たから]:treasure, 出てくる[でてくる]:to come out/to appear/to turn up, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
何かお宝が
出てくるかもしれないぜ
宝[たから]:treasure
んっ？　お宝ってなんだよ
What kind of treasure?
キラバグだよ
Kirabugs.
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 鍵[かぎ, カギ]:key|lock, 鍵[けん]:key (of a piano, etc.)
しまった！　鍵をさしたままだ
Damn it!
It escaped with my key!
捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize, お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
捕まえた！
お姉ちゃん 捕まえたよ
Got it!
Sis, I got it!
バグる:to behave buggily (software)/to act up/to behave strangely, 普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 倍[ばい]:twice/double|times, 値[あたい, ね]:price|value|value|, 値[ち]:level/value
（ダイチ）
キラバグって 普通の30倍の値が
ついたってウワサのか？
Kirabugs...
Do you mean, the ones valued at more than thirty times the regular price?
駅[えき]:station, 残骸[ざんがい]:ruins/wreckage, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（ガチャギリ）ああ 駅ビルで
その残骸を見たヤツがいたらしい
Yeah.
Someone happened to see fragments of it at the station.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 一獲[いっかく]:one grab, 千金[せんきん]:1000 pounds/1000 kan/1000 yen, 狙う[ねらう]:to aim at
きっとイサコのヤツも
一獲千金を狙ってるんだ
I'm sure Isako plans to get rich in one go.
乗っかる[のっかる]:to get on/to climb on, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
これに乗っからない理由はねえぜ
There's no reason why she wouldn't want this prize!
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed
なるほど
I see!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 楽[らく]:comfort/ease|raku pottery
それなら
こんな仕事も楽なもんだぜ
In that case, this job is a piece of cake!
役立つ[やくだつ]:to be useful/to be helpful/to serve the purpose
役立たずめ！
Those worthless fools!
やはり:too/also|still, 今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 引き寄せる[ひきよせる]:to draw or pull something towards oneself (e.g. chair)
やはり 今までどおり
ペットで引き寄せるべきだったか
I should've just used a pet,
as I've been doing up till now!
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
そうだ！　もしかして あそこに…
That's right!
If by any chance it's over there...
（ヤサコ）京子？
Kyoko!
待て！
Wait!
What's... this?
何… これ？
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
うわっ…
（イサコ）バカ 早く出ろ！
You idiot! Get out of here, quickly!
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
しまった！
Damn it!
開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||, 工場[こうじょう, こうば]:factory/plant/mill
（ヤサコ）開かないわ
廃工場なのに なんで？
It won't open.
Why? Isn't this factory abandoned?
なんてマヌケなんだ
I'm such an idiot...
I never imagined I'd fall into my own trap!
仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps), トラップ:trap, 引っ掛かる[ひっかかる]:to be caught in|to stop by|to get mixed up in (trouble)||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
自分で仕掛けたトラップに
引っ掛かるなんて
A trap?
トラップ:trap
トラップ？
I would have confined it here
いざというとき:when it's important/when it comes to the crunch/when push comes to shove, 閉じ込める[とじこめる]:to lock up/to shut up/to imprison, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
いざというとき
ここに閉じ込める予定だったんだ
in case of an emergency.
Confined what?
閉じ込める[とじこめる]:to lock up/to shut up/to imprison
閉じ込めるって何を？
イリーガル:illegal
イリーガルだ
The Illegal.
閉じ込める[とじこめる]:to lock up/to shut up/to imprison
自分のほうが閉じ込められるとはな
I can't believe that I ended up here instead.
イリーガル:illegal, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 閉じ込める[とじこめる]:to lock up/to shut up/to imprison
イリーガルなら
電脳壁で閉じ込められるでしょ？
I thought the only way to confine an Illegal was with cyberweaponry.
扉[とびら]:door/gate|title page, 閉める[しめる]:to close/to shut
なんで扉まで閉めるのよ
So why did you need to close the door?
バッテリー:battery, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
バッテリーが残っているのに
気づかなかった
I didn't notice it had some battery power left.
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy), 作動[さどう]:operation/functioning/running, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
それが暗号で
偶然 作動したらしい
Apparently, it moved somehow, thanks to the encode.
I know!
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
そうだ！　電話で誰か呼べば…
Let's call for help!
Out of Reach
Unable to Connect
圏外[けんがい]:(being) out of range (e.g. mobile network, radar, missiles)/(being) out of contention/(being) beyond influence
（ヤサコ）圏外…
（イサコ）ムダだ
Out of reach...
It's no use.
I blocked the signal from this place on purpose.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 発信[はっしん]:dispatch/despatch/transmission, 遮断[しゃだん]:isolation/cut off/blockade
こちらからの発信は
遮断してある
But it's possible to receive—
受信[じゅしん]:reception (e.g. radio)/receipt (e.g. email message)
受信はできるがな
Why did you do such a thing?!
なんで そんなことするのよ
Hey, there's a way to get out of here, right?
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
ねえ 外に出る方法は
あるんでしょ？
There isn't.
ないわ
It's possible to open it from the outside,
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
外からは開けられるけど
中からはムリよ
but impossible to do so from the inside.
Why?!
なんで？
I didn't predict this situation.
想定外[そうていがい]:beyond expectations/beyond what one expected/not foreseen
こんなの想定外よ
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions)
お前さえ
こんな所に現れなければ
If only you hadn't popped up like that.
So it's my fault?!
私のせい？
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
天沢(あまさわ)さんがこんなことしてるなんて
私が知るわけないじゃない！
But how could I have known
that you were doing all this in the first place?
フン！
Oh yeah, Kyoko is here, too!
そうだ 京子がいる！
（イサコ）何？
What?
She's around here somewhere.
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 大声[おおごえ, たいせい]:loud voice, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
（ヤサコ）近くにいるのよ
大声で呼んで開け方を教えれば…
If we call for her out loud, and tell her how to open...
Why didn't you say so in the first place?!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
それを早く言え！
Over there!
いた！
（イサコ）どこだ？
Where?
Oh, Kyoko...
ったら:indicates supposition/if ... then|(typically after someone's name) indicates exasperation
京子ったら…
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
んっ… マズい
（ヤサコ）んっ？
This is bad!
Oh no! An Illegal!
イリーガル:illegal
ヤダ… イリーガル！
It wants to enter the pet.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 逃げ込む[にげこむ]:to take refuge in/to succeed in running away, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
ヤツはペットの中に逃げ込む気だ
Enter the pet?
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
ペットの中？
Illegals can only survive
イリーガル:illegal, 生き延びる[いきのびる]:to survive/to live long
（イサコ）
イリーガルが生き延びられるのは
in an obsolete Space or inside cybermateria.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables, 体内[たいない]:interior of the body
古い空間と
電脳生物の体内だけなんだ
It's useless...
回線[かいせん]:circuit/line
ダメだ この回線も違う
This circuit is no good, either.
What are you doing, Isako?
ねえ 何やってるの？　イサコ
Don't call me Isako!
イサコって言うな
S-Sorry.
なさる:to do
ご…　ごめんなさい
I'm looking for a way to open the door.
開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（イサコ）
ドアを開ける方法を探してるんだ
So stop bothering me.
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
邪魔するな
Listen, Isa—
あの… イサ…
あっ 天沢さん 私…
Amasawa, I—
I don't want to be your friend.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（イサコ）あんたたちと
友達になる気はないわ
I already told you that.
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
こないだ言ったとおりよ
Oh, is that so?
そ… そうですか
Oh!
師匠[ししょう]:master/teacher|coach who owns his stable
そうだ じゃあ 師匠としてはどう？
Then how about becoming my master?
That last time, when you spilled metabugs out of a secret Space,
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently, 駅[えき]:station, 秘密[ひみつ]:secret|secret|esoteric teachings, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
ほら こないだの
駅ビルの秘密の空間から
取り出す[とりだす]:to take out/to produce|to fetch
メタバグを取り出したんでしょ？
it looked like a magical power...
まるで:quite/entirely|as if, 魔法[まほう]:magic/witchcraft/sorcery, 使い[つかい]:errand|messenger|familiar spirit|, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
まるで魔法使いみたいだわ
I'd like to use it, too!
憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire
私 憧れちゃう
I beg you, please let me be your disciple!
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please, 弟子[でし, ていし]:pupil/disciple/adherent
お願い 弟子にして！
断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave
断る！
Absolutely not!
See?
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
なあ？　こいつは
ちゃんと動きやがる
This stuff really works!
If that girl is after the kirabugs,
狙う[ねらう]:to aim at
あの女が
キラバグを狙ってるとすれば
we just have to be patient.
しばらく:little while/short while|a while, 我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance, 一手[いって]:move (in game)/method/single-handed, 一手[ひとて, いっしゅ]:one hand|one's own effort
しばらく我慢の一手だぜ
But the kirabug is just an urban legend, right?
バグる:to behave buggily (software)/to act up/to behave strangely, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
しかし キラバグって
都市伝説じゃないのか？
What urban legend?
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
どんな都市伝説なんすか？
Supposedly, a legendary hacker obtained the kirabug
伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, ハッカー:hacker, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
ある伝説のハッカーが
そのキラバグを手に入れたんだ
from "the other side".
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
あっちからな
But when he tried to bring it here,
呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine), 途端[とたん]:just (now, at the moment, etc.)/just as/in the act of, 砕ける[くだける]:to break (into pieces)|to collapse|to become less formal||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
だが こっちに呼び出した途端
砕けて死んでしまったそうだ
it shattered into pieces and died.
Died?
生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
（ダイチ）死んだ？
キラバグって生き物(もん)なのか？
So it's a living creature?
Yeah.
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
（ガチャギリ）
ああ その都市伝説ではな
At least according to the legend.
And so, the remains of the kirabug are what we call metabugs.
化石[かせき]:fossil/petrifaction/fossilization
そして その死んだキラバグの
化石がメタバグなんだ
（一同）へえー
So the kirabug is a living metabug?
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
じゃあ キラバグは
生きたメタバグってことか
I wonder if he has legs and runs...
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth), 走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
足でも生えて走り出すんですかね
Yasako!
ヤサコ どこ？
Where are you?
Hey! Hold it right there!
近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with
（ダイチ）おい ここに近づくな！
Daichi!
（フミエ）ダイチ！
なんで ここにいるの？
What are you doing here?
That's my line!
セリフ:serif, セリフ:speech/words/one's lines, とっとと:quickly/at once/right away, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（ダイチ）それはこっちのセリフだ
とっとと帰れ！
Now get the hell outta here!
Shut up!
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
（フミエ）うるさい！
（一同）うわっ…
C-Cut it out!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
や… やめろ！
危ねえじゃねえか！
That's dangerous!
You're in no position
指図[さしず]:instruction/mandate/directions, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
私に指図するなんて
10年 早いわよ
to give me orders!
You're the one who has to leave.
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
あんたが帰れ！
んん～ あのチビスケのブスエが！
That damn shrimpy Busue!
（イサコ）チェッ これも違う
Not this one, either.
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
ああ… 暑くなってきたわね
It's getting hotter in here...
話しかける[はなしかける]:to address (someone)/to accost a person|to begin to talk
（イサコ）話しかけるな
Don't talk to me!
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
天沢さんってさ
あんまり幸せじゃないでしょ？
Amasawa, you must not be very happy, huh?
幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
人間 幸せに生きるのが一番よ
People should live a happy life.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger
さすがに天沢さんも
そう思うでしょ？
I bet you think so too, right?
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially
（イサコ）特に そうは思わない
No, I don't.
そ… そうですか
Is...
Is that so...?
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
手伝おうか？
Do you need some help?
しょう:workman/artisan|craft, しょう:quotient|dealing/dealer
もう しょうがない子ね
What am I going to do with you?
よいしょっと
外れる[はずれる]:to be disconnected/to get out of place/to be off
ほら 外れたわ
Okay, it's free.
幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
天沢さんに
幸せに生きるコツを教えてあげる
I'll teach you a secret for living happily.
拒む[こばむ]:to refuse/to reject/to decline
人を拒まないことよ
You shouldn't reject people.
決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least
なんでも１人でやろうと思っても
決してできないものよ
It's impossible to do everything by yourself in life.
他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
誰だって他人の力が必要なのよ
Everybody needs other people's help.
他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, 拒む[こばむ]:to refuse/to reject/to decline, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
あんたが他人を拒まないのは
相手のためじゃない
The reason why you don't reject others,
isn't because you're thinking of them.
自分のためだ
（ヤサコ）えっ？
You do it for yourself.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 調子を合わせる[ちょうしをあわせる]:to harmonize with/to keep in tune with|to go along with, 意見[いけん]:opinion/view/comment, 合わせる[あわせる]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||
（イサコ）友達と調子を合わせて
意見を合わせて
You adapt yourself in order to live in harmony with other people...
You adapt your point of view...
言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
自分の言いたいことも言えない
そんな幸せならいらないわ
You can't even say what you want...
If that's happiness, no thanks.
京子！
Kyoko!
幼児[ようじ]:infant/baby|child over 1 but not yet of school age
おい そこの幼児！
Hey, kid!
サブドメイン:subdomain, 解除[かいじょ]:cancellation/rescinding/release
サブドメインの
キーファイルを解除してくれ
Turn the lock on the subdomain key files off!
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
それじゃ 聞こえても
意味 分からないわよ
She wouldn't understand that even if she heard you!
じゃあ お前がやれ
Then you do it!
ロック:lock
京子！　ここのロックを
か い じょ し て！
Kyoko!
The lock...
u-n-l-o-c-k it!
具体的[ぐたいてき]:concrete/tangible/definite
具体的に言わないと
分かるわけないでしょ
If you don't tell her how to actually do it,
she'll never guess how.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition
じゃ… じゃあ
ちゃんと説明してよ
Th-Then explain it clearly to her!
ったら:indicates supposition/if ... then|(typically after someone's name) indicates exasperation
ハァ… あの子ったら もう
What am I supposed to do with that girl?
それにしても―
Why is that virus wandering around here?
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), ウイルス:virus, うろつく:to loiter/to putter|to be confused from not knowing what to do, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
なんで あんなウイルスが
うろついてるのかしら？
ウイルス:virus
（イサコ）あれはウイルスじゃない
That's not a virus.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（ヤサコ）どういうこと？
What do you mean?
フッ 知りたいか？
You want to know?
Yes.
呪う[のろう]:to curse/to put a curse on/to detest intensely, 呪う[まじなう]:to pray that one avoids disaster or illness|to pray for the death or misfortune of another|to treat illness with prayer, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
あれは呪われた生き物
That is
a doomed creature.
呪う[のろう]:to curse/to put a curse on/to detest intensely, 呪う[まじなう]:to pray that one avoids disaster or illness|to pray for the death or misfortune of another|to treat illness with prayer, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
呪われた生き物？
A doomed... creature?
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, ゆがみ:strain/distortion/deformation, ゆがみ:hairdo, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 出来[しゅったい]:occurrence/happening/taking place, 出来[でき]:workmanship|grades|quality (e.g. of a crop)|, 損[そん]:loss/damage|disadvantage, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
（イサコ）空間のゆがみで生まれた
出来損ないの生き物
An incomplete being created from a distortion in the Space.
出てくる[でてくる]:to come out/to appear/to turn up, 以前[いぜん]:ago/since/before, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, すっかり:all/completely/totally, なくす:to lose something|to get rid of
こっちに出てくる以前の記憶を
すっかりなくしてるけどね
They've completely lost their memories about the time before they came here.
例えば[たとえば]:for example/for instance/e.g., 何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
例えば そう…
自分が何者だったのかすら
For example,
what they were in the past.
あの世[あのよ]:the other world/world of the dead/netherworld, 亡者[もうじゃ]:the dead
ヤツらは言ってみれば
あの世の亡者よ
In other words, they're like the inhabitants of the netherworld.
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, あてど:aim/goal, さまよう:to loiter/to putter/to prowl, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
それが消えずに
あてどなく さまよい続けている
They carry on forever, wandering without a goal.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 襲う[おそう]:to attack|to succeed (someone in a post, role, etc.)|to make a sudden visit
（ヤサコ）なぜペットを襲うの？
Why do they attack pets?
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（イサコ）ペットの体など
本当は問題じゃない
The real issue isn't the body of the pet.
単なる[たんなる]:mere/simple/sheer, 避難[ひなん]:taking refuge/finding shelter/evacuation, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
そこは単なる避難場所にすぎない
It's just a place to take shelter.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 溶ける[とける]:to melt/to thaw/to fuse, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
新しい空間では そうしないと
すぐに体が溶けてしまうからだ
In fact, if they don't do so in a new Space,
their body disintegrates.
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
彼らが本当に欲しいものは別にある
But there's something special they aim for.
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
自分の正体を
忘れてしまっているのに
Although they've forgotten their nature,
本能[ほんのう]:instinct, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
それだけは本能が覚えているんだ
they do remember one thing: their instinct.
それは…
And that is...
子供[こども]:child/children, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, 本能[ほんのう]:instinct
人間の子供に近づくという本能
the instinct to get close to kids.
子供[こども]:child/children
子供に？
To kids?
入り込む[はいりこむ, いりこむ]:to go into/to come into|to become complicated, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（イサコ）
ヤツらが本当に入り込みたい場所は
The place they really want to get inside is
子供[こども]:child/children, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
子供の電脳体
the cyberbodies of children!
（ヤサコ）
えっ そんな… どうして？
No way...
But why?
知りたいの？　本当に知りたい？
Do you want to know?
Do you really want to know?
な… 何よ
Wh-What is it?
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
（イサコ）教えてあげる
I'll tell you then.
食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
ヤツらはね 食べるのよ
You must know
that they eat...
子供[こども]:child/children, 魂[たましい, だましい]:soul/spirit, 魂[こん]:Yang energy/spirit
子供の魂をね
kids' souls!
魂[たましい, だましい]:soul/spirit, 魂[こん]:Yang energy/spirit
魂を？
Souls?
内側[うちがわ, ないそく]:inside/interior/inner part, 潜り込む[もぐりこむ]:to slip into/to crawl into (under)|to sneak into
そうよ 内側に潜り込んで
ムシャムシャとね
Exactly.
It sneaks inside your body,
and gnaws away at you!
That's...
そ… そんなことあるわけない
That's completely impossible!
イリーガル:illegal, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
だって イリーガルは
電脳世界のものじゃない
The Illegals are from the virtual world, aren't they?
（イサコ）それがあるのよ
There is a way.
呪う[のろう]:to curse/to put a curse on/to detest intensely, 呪う[まじなう]:to pray that one avoids disaster or illness|to pray for the death or misfortune of another|to treat illness with prayer, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
呪われた方法がね
A cursed way...
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate
（イサコ）都市伝説で
語られるだけになってるけど
It's only been reported in urban legends,
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality), 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, 子供[こども]:child/children
実際に食われた子供がいるのよ
but in reality, some kids have actually been eaten.
そんなバカな…
That's... completely absurd...
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
あんたも気をつけたほうがいい
You'd better be careful, too.
好物[こうぶつ]:favourite dish (favorite)/favourite food
ヤツらの好物は
Their favorite target is
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, めでたい:happy/auspicious|naive, 無防備[むぼうび]:defenseless/defenceless, 子供[こども]:child/children, 魂[たましい, だましい]:soul/spirit, 魂[こん]:Yang energy/spirit
あんたみたいな
おめでたい無防備な子供の魂
the helpless, happy soul of a kid
exactly like you!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめてよ！
Cut it out!
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
気をつけな
Watch out.
気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 忍び寄る[しのびよる]:to creep/to steal up/to draw near unnoticed
ヤツらは気づかない間に
忍び寄ってくる
They sneak inside you when you least expect it,
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
そして食っちまうんだ
and they eat it.
魂[たましい, だましい]:soul/spirit, 魂[こん]:Yang energy/spirit
お前の魂をな！
Your soul, got it?
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめて！
Knock it off!
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
ハハハハッ 信じた？
Did you believe it?
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 作り話[つくりばなし]:fiction/made-up story/fable
バカね ウソよ
全部 私の作り話
You're such a fool.
It was all a lie.
I made everything up.
作り話[つくりばなし]:fiction/made-up story/fable
作り話？
Made it up...?
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), 単なる[たんなる]:mere/simple/sheer, コンピューターウイルス:computer virus
あれは あんたの友達が言うとおり
単なるコンピューターウイルスよ
It's exactly like your friend says.
It's just a computer virus.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 妙[みょう]:strange|wonder|cleverness, 変異[へんい]:variation/rogue (something), 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
最近 妙な変異を
起こしてるみたいだけどね
Even if it has been acting strangely recently.
だます:to trick/to cheat|to coax
だましたのね！
So you tricked me!
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, ハッカー:hacker, ばらまく:to scatter/to disseminate (e.g. a rumor)|to distribute widely (e.g. leaflets)
もともとは どこかのハッカーが
ばらまいたそうよ
I heard that a hacker originally spread it,
いろんな:various, 機器[きき]:device/equipment/machinery, 誤動作[ごどうさ]:malfunction
いろんな機器を
誤動作させるためにね
in order to take down numerous machines.
意地悪[いじわる]:malicious/ill-tempered/unkind
もう意地悪！
You meanie!
Out of Reach
Unable to Connect
（ヤサコ）あっ
（イサコ）どうした？
What is it?
一瞬[いっしゅん]:instant/moment/for an instant, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
今 一瞬つながった
（イサコ）なんだと？
It connected for an instant!
What?
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, ポーズ:pose, ポーズ:baozi/Chinese steamed bun
おい もう一度 さっきのポーズだ
Hey!
Take that pose again!
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
足を開け
Spread your legs.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, なさる:to do, エッチ:H/h
や… やめなさいよ エッチ
Stop touching me, you pervert!
聞ける[きける]:to tell, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 電波[でんぱ, デムパ]:electromagnetic wave/radio wave|saying strange things, 漏れ[もれ]:leakage|omission|I
（イサコ）言うことを聞け
きっと電波の漏れがあるんだ
Do as I say!
The signal must be leaking in.
So I'm replacing an antenna?
アンテナ:antenna, 代わり[かわり]:substitute|stand-in|compensation||, 代わり[がわり]:substitute for ...
私ってアンテナ代わり？
あっ キュウちゃんだ！
The Kyuu-chans!
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
何？　マズいぞ それは…
What?!
We're in big trouble!
ポーズ:pose, ポーズ:baozi/Chinese steamed bun
（ヤサコ）京子！
（イサコ）そのポーズだ
Kyoko!
That position!
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
えっ？
（イサコ）動くな
Don't move!
靴[くつ]:shoes/boots/footwear, うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
待って！　く… 靴
うわあ～！
Wait!
My shoes...!
ウンチ！
Poop!
幼児[ようじ]:infant/baby|child over 1 but not yet of school age, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 崩れる[くずれる]:to collapse|to get out of shape|to break down||
おい 幼児 早く戻れ！
そこは崩れるぞ
Hey, kid!
Come over here, quick!
It's gonna fall!
ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful
ゆっくり こっちに来るのよ
できる？
Come here... slowly.
You can do it.
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 歩く[あるく]:to walk
普通に歩くの　分かる？
Walk normally.
Got it?
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 一歩[いっぽ]:(a) step|level|small degree
怖くない 一歩ずつよ
Nothing to be afraid of.
Step by step.
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
そうよ うまいわ
Just like that.
Good girl.
いでる:to go/to come
おいで
Come...
Here!
跳ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
こっちだ 跳べ！
Jump!
Kyoko!
京子！
ハッ… 京子
Kyoko!
じっと:motionlessly (e.g. stand, wait)/(be) still|fixedly (e.g. gaze, stare), 他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
ほら じっとして
他に痛いところないわね？
C'mon, dry those tears.
You don't have any other scratches, do you?
（ヤサコ）１人にしてごめんね
Sorry for leaving you alone.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 求める[もとめる]:to want|to request|to seek|, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|
（イサコ）
古い空間を求めて外へ出たか
So it was looking for an obsolete Space, and when it came out...
イリーガル:illegal, かなり:considerably/fairly/quite, 量[りょう]:quantity/amount/volume, 量[はか]:progress, 含む[ふくむ, くくむ]:to contain|to hold in the mouth|to bear in mind|
あのイリーガル
かなりの量のキラバグを含んでいた
That Illegal
had a big kirabug inside it.
逃がす[にがす]:to set free/to let go|to miss (e.g. a chance)
逃がすものか
I won't let him get away.
Amasawa, wait.
（ヤサコ）天沢さん 待って
Thank you for helping Kyoko.
助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
京子を助けてくれて… ありがとう
It was nothing.
別に
I wonder...
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
私たち…
if we really can't be friends.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
やっぱり友達になれないのかな？
I...
（イサコ）
それはないと言ったはずよ
already told you so, didn't I?
必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
私が必要なものを
あんたは持ってないわ
You don't have the thing I need.
Is that so...
（ヤサコ）そう…
（イサコ）でも
But...
Nobody in this world really knows
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
先のことは分からないわ
この世界の誰にも
what will happen next.
（フミエ）なんですって？
What did you say?!
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, ひと言[ひとこと, いちげん]:single word/a few words/brief comment
キラバグだなんて
ひと言も言っとらん
I never said the word kirabug.
そもそも:in the first place/to begin with|... the heck (e.g. "what the heck?"), 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
そもそも何をマンタに記憶させたか
わしも覚えとらんのじゃ
After all, I don't even remember what I recorded in Manta.
Mega-baa!
メガばあ！
Be patient.
解凍[かいとう]:thaw/defrosting|decompression (e.g. of a file)
まあ 待っとれ　今 解凍中じゃ
I'm uncompressing it now.
Decompressing
I'm sure it's a very valuable item!
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 値打ち[ねうち]:value/worth/price, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
絶対 値打ちもんに決まっとる
There it is!
It's on my husband's head.
（フミエ）出た！
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||
（メガばあ）ん… んっ？
（フミエ）頭？
The head?
Oh, I remember now!
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
おおー 思い出した
The shining thing was my husband's head!
光り物[ひかりもの]:luminous body like a shooting star|any bright metal|sliced fish with the silver skin left on (iwashi, aji, sayori, sanma, kohada, etc.), 旦那[だんな]:master (of a house, shop, etc.)|husband (informal)|sir||, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||
光り物は
わしの旦那の頭 そのものじゃ
What the hell am I supposed to do with a third of this?!
割[わり]:rate|profit|assignment||, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, どない:what kind/what sort/how
んなもん ３割もらって
どないすんじゃ～！
There's a weak signal coming from an obsolete Space.
わずか:only/merely/(a) little, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response
わずかに古い空間の反応が出ている
And right next to here is...
この先[このさき]:beyond this point/from now on/after this
この先は…
the school.
学校[がっこう]:school
学校か
Preview
Next time on Dennou Coil:
The summer festival and the duel.
The Summer Festival and the Duel
See you next time!
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
夏祭り[なつまつり]:summer festival, 果たし合い[はたしあい]:duel
〝夏祭り、
そして果たし合い 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに